Those are work companions.
那是班搭子
We spend a considerable amount of time together each week.
每周按说待的时间也不少
About 40 hours in total.
有40个小时待在一起
But after work, though,
但是呢下班了啊
if we pass each other on the street,
如果在大街上擦肩而过
we might not even say hello to each other.
可能都不跟对方打个招呼
Chatting
聊天的
with someone to vent to
有吐槽搭子
and a gossip buddy, right?
八卦搭子对吧
we can complain together about
互相一起骂骂
the weirdos we've met recently
最近遇见的奇葩
and talk a lot in the group chat every day
每天在群聊里说好多话
but we might not see each other in person more than once a year
但是呢一年也不一定能见一次面
there's also a dining partner
还有吃饭搭子
and a drinking buddy
酒搭子
Party buddies
聚会搭子
We might gather for dinner every Friday
每周五可能大家在一块吃饭
have drinks and hang out
喝酒聚会啊
sing and have a great time
唱K开开心心
get cozy and close
勾肩搭背
seen each other a bit tipsy
见过对方喝多了
even puke in front of each other
吐在自己面前
but if you really dig deeper
但是你要真往下问
we haven't had any heart-to-heart talks
双方没谈过走心的话
Most likely, they don't even know what the other person does for a living.
很可能都不知道对方究竟是干什么的
Lunch buddy
饭搭子
Drinking buddy
酒搭子
Photo-taking buddy
拍照搭子
Travel buddy
旅游搭子
Group chat buddy
群聊搭子
We're all buddies
大家呢都是搭子
We serve as containers and tools for each other
互相给对方做容器和工具
Clean and simple
清清爽爽
One encounter, one relationship
一期一会亲密关系
We don't need that anymore After all, we can have a bed buddy We can have a dating partner We can have a male best friend We can have a female bro, right? What if bed buddies fall for each other? And accidentally say something like I like you It was enough to make you break out in a cold sweat right there.
这种东西不需要了 反正可以有床搭子 有约会搭子 有男闺蜜 有女兄弟对吧 你说床搭子之间睡上头了 不小心说了一句 我喜欢你 当场就得惊出一身冷汗
The next day, you’d be kicking yourself and scrambling for solutions.
后悔第二天赶紧找辙啊
She deliberately let on that she had other male contestants in mind.
故意透露出自己还有别的男嘉宾
female contestants,
女嘉宾
just to avoid any misunderstandings.
免得对方误会
Even if they occasionally dated someone,
就算偶尔谈个恋爱
it was more like a trial run,
那也是走走看
not thinking of committing to a long-term relationship.
想着和对方走到底
staying true to one person all the way through.
从一而终嚯
That's a bit too old school.
那有点太old school了
Hey, dog.
狗子啊
I was thinking it wasn't like this before.
我寻思着以前不这样
Back then, people were only nodding acquaintances.
以前呢大家只有点头之交
Then casual friends.
然后普通朋友
Good Friends
好朋友
And really close friends.
还有特别好的朋友
We were all complete individuals.
大家都是完整的人
There was a huge gray area between us.
互相之间呢是一条巨大的灰度
When you hit it off and mutually recognize each other
聊得来互相认可
the relationship can deepen
关系呢就可以往深里走走
Indeed, some relationships are about providing value to each other
确实啊有些关系是彼此提供一些价值的
But there isn’t a clear-cut boundary in between
但是这中间并没有一条绝对清晰的界限
that neither party should cross
是双方不能逾越的
Of course, colleagues can be friends Pen pals can meet in person too But later, I came to realize This is actually quite normal When you really think about it, friends can be quite scary. What if a friend and their significant other have a fight?
同事之间当然可以交朋友 笔友之间也可以见面 但是呢后来我也想明白了啊 这其实挺正常挺正常的 朋友这东西细细想太吓人了 你说朋友和对象之间吵架了
They get emo.
Emo了
And they call to say
打电话过来说
they want to come over to vent and talk it out.
想来我家倾诉倾诉
Then maybe stay over for the night.
然后收留一晚
You know, that’s what friends are for.
你说这也都是朋友
I can’t just turn them away, can I?
我不能不开门吧
Or what if a friend has surgery?
或者朋友做手术了
I have to go check on you in the hospital, right?
躺在医院我总得去看看吧
You and your friend both got pretty tipsy.
你和朋友之间俩人喝多了
You talked about everything.
什么都聊啊
Then you mentioned another mutual friend.
聊到另外认识的一个共友
He really can't stand that person.
他特别讨厌那个人
I actually really like that person.
我特别喜欢那个人
Before we knew it, we started to clash.
一言不合俩还聊别扭了
It ended up ruining the evening.
当场弄得不欢而散
Things have been awkward ever since.
后续别别扭扭的
We should still find a chance to reconcile, right?
还得找机会和解对吧
So once friends get close enough,
所以只要是朋友处熟了
those social boundaries will eventually break down.
那点社交边界早晚就是绷不住的
And real life is full of surprises.
而且现实生活是充满意外的
As friends,
作为朋友
you need to be there for each other,
你得接住对方
to handle the uncertainties that might come up.
有可能发生的不确定性
But what's the issue?
可问题是什么呢
It's about friends from the pre-Internet era.
是前互联网时代的朋友
We all know each other inside out
大家都是知根知底的
Either we're colleagues
你说大家要么是同事
Or people who work together
要一起做事的人
Or our parents know each other
要么呢互相之间爸妈认识
Or we're neighbors
要么是街坊邻居
But where can you find such an environment nowadays?
可现在哪还有这种环境呢
New people you meet are like dark boxes
新遇到的人对你来说都是乌漆嘛
It's hard to say what's really inside So, from another perspective You go out to make friends You go out to fall in love It's like giving someone else the chance and the right to hurt you
黑的一个黑盒子里面有什么真不好说 所以呢从另一个角度来说 你去交朋友 你去谈恋爱 相当于给了另外一个人伤害你的机会和权利
We're all human, after all
咱们人心都是肉长的
How many times can a person be hurt, really?
一个人又能被伤害几次呢
More importantly
更重要的是
We're not just cold towards others
我们不光是对别人
We're also just as indifferent to ourselves
我们对自己其实也是一样的冷漠
Just as distant
一样的疏离
You said that when studying from a young age, you shouldn't consider your interests and hobbies.
你说从小学习的时候不能考虑兴趣爱好
When working, you shouldn't think about whether it's comfortable or not.
上班工作的时候不能考虑舒不舒服
When talking to your boss,
和领导谈话的时候
you can't really care about things like dignity.
那点什么尊严不尊严的就不能在意了
Even with the closest relationships,
甚至和最亲的关系
if couples argue,
情侣之间要是吵架了
sometimes you can't just stick to the facts.
有时候你也不能讲道理
When we treat others as partners,
我们在把别人看做搭子的时候
we've already turned ourselves into strangers.
其实已经早把自己变成陌生人了
You can only barely survive like this.
你只有这样才能凑合的活下去
We can't even call ourselves complete, natural beings anymore.
咱们自己都不能称作一个完整的自然的人了
So, we can only look for partners outside, right?
那对外可不就只能找搭子吗
I don't even know myself.
甚至我自己也不知道
What's inside this black box of mine?
我自己这个黑盒子打开到底是什么啊
I don't want to know what others are like either.
我也不想知道别人是什么
To avoid being shocked,
我为了不要惊吓
I
我
would rather give up those surprises and warmth as well.
宁可把那些惊喜还有温暖也给抛弃掉
We show each other the side we've designed to present. We exchange a limited amount of value within our control. Happily. Casually. Without owing anything to each other. It's all good this way. I think I understand it now.
咱们互相把自己设计好的那一面展露给对方 交换一下有限的在控制范围之内的价值 高高兴兴 轻轻松松 两不相欠 这样就挺好 我想明白是想明白了
But seeing you guys being completely open and honest with each other,
可是看见你们这些狗子互相赤身裸体
Treating each other with sincerity,
坦诚相待
Spending every day together,
每天都在一块儿
Fighting when it's time to fight,
该打架该打架
Hugging when it's time to hug,
该搂抱还是搂抱
There's not so much complexity between us,
互相之间没那么多复杂的
It's like treating each other as just another dog.
就是把对方也当做另一条狗子来对待
So I can't help but wonder,
所以我呢会忍不住想
From outside the cage,
笼子外的
We see inside the cage,
我们看到笼子内的
Do you ever have a moment where you're not sure,
你们会不会有那么一瞬间搞不清楚
Who's really in the cage?
究竟谁在笼子里呢
What do you think, dog?
狗子你说呢